A Guide to Materials on Women
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Harrison Family Papers 1720-1960, ca. 1000 items.
  Correspondence, diaries, and business papers of the Harrison and Meems families including: typescript copies of correspondence between Betsy Ambler Carrington which discuss events in and around Yorktown, the British invasion of Virginia, and the government's evacuation of Richmond for Charlottesville, Virginia (see also #6403-i & 6723); and, a certification of Florence Blair is a widow of a Revolutionary war veteran and is entitled to her husband's pension. #7661.
- Atcheson Hench World War II Collection 1936-1945, 119 items.
  Contains correspondence between Mr. and Mrs. Hench in regards to World War II and Mrs. Hench's speeches and programs for organizations involved in the war effort. #2504-g.
- Henkel Family Papers 1765-1955, 325 items
  Papers (many in German) of the Henkel family of New Market, Virginia, consist of correspondence which is primarily concerned with church affairs, family matters, and the printing press business founded and managed by the family. Of special interest are the diaries of Anna Maria Henkel for several years (1851-1876). #38-241
- Henkel Press 1890's, 24 items.
  Twenty-three block prints from the Henkel press as well as the Reverend Socrates Henkel's membership certificate in the Woman's Home and Foreign Missionary Society (June 24, 1891). #746
- John Herndon Miscellaneous Virginia Collection, 28 boxes
  Largely unprocessed collection; however contains important documents relating to Christ Church in Alexandria, Virginia, with some documents relating to women and genealogy. #1570
- Henry Heth Papers 1763-1841, 4000 items.
  Business, personal, and legal correspondence of Major Henry Heth (d. 1822), a Revolutionary soldier, a member of the Federalist party and a Richmond and Norfolk areas of Virginia businessman who owned the Black Heath coal pits. There is some scattered personal correspondence between women. #38-114
- Mrs. Hill Diary 1862-1863, 1 item.
  A diary kept during 1862-1863 recording her days in Chapel Hill, North Carolina. Mrs. Hill had fled Virginia and lived in a boarding house with a number of other families. She notes male callers and the weather, but little of the war. #6960.
- Holladay Family Papers 1760 [1820-1940] 1966, 295 items.
  Personal and business papers of the Holladay family of Spotsylvania County, Virginia, especially Lewis, Waller, Henry Thompson, and John Mansfield Holladay. Of special interest are four diaries, 1851-1861, of Mary Jane Boggs Holladay (1833-1861) in 9703
- Charlton Gilmore Holland Papers 1940-1945, ca. 1200 items.
  Letters exchanged between Dr. and Mrs. Charlton G. Holland during World War II, when he was on leave from the medical faculty of the University of Virginia and with the Army Medical Corps in the Pacific. #2876
- Charlton Gilmore Holland Papers 1937-1958, ca. 400 items.
  Professional and personal correspondence of Charlton Gilmore Holland (1911- ), photographs, German road maps, clippings from German papers and miscellaneous printed material, chiefly from his German trip. Letters during the 1950s, from Clifford Evans, Associate Curator, and Betty J. Meggers. Research Associate, of the Division of Archaeology at the Smithsonian Institution, discuss their trip to Ecuador and their archaeological finds on the Rio Napo. #3572
- Hollins College 1853, 1891, 2 items.
  Printed circular of September 16, 1853 by Charles Cocke concerning the Female Seminary at Botetourt Springs, now Hollins College [filed as Broadside 1853 .C63]. There is also a printed program for an art recital at Hollins for April 24, 1891. #545.
- Lucy Holmes Album 1828-1848, 1 item.
  Lucy Holmes' album of manuscript poems, including a poem by Edgar Allan Poe entitled Original. Microfilm 1778; (#3459)
- John Hook Papers 1803-1862, 131 items
  John Hook, a resident of Franklin County, Virginia, concerned himself with commercial and agricultural affairs in southern and western Virginia, primarily tobacco cultivation. Items of interest are a Court Order to John Hook to allow Nanny Page, a slave, time to procure Testimony. Also there are six letters [1862-1863] to Sarah/Sallie Hale from various persons. #38-28
- John Hook Additional Papers 1787-1887
  Additional papers of John Hook and others. "Unknown" to Sallie Hale, September 3, 1862, describes her sister Nannie's death from typhoid; "Cousin Jimmie" to Sallie, January 14, 1862, Sallie has warned Jimmie about flirting with the young ladies at it leads to sad results. However, Sallie admitted to Jimmie that it was very pleasant thing and she had had some experience. Jimmie teases her about breaking hearts. A letter from Jane P. Stegal, (Sallie's aunt) to Sallie Hale, March 29, 1862, detailing family news as well as Civil War news, especially the rumor that McClellan has landed 10,000 troops at Newport News, Virginia. #247
- Houston-Willson Papers 1831-1926, 22 items.
  Include letter, May 6, 1851, Mrs. William Willson to "Dear Sister," with a long passage concerning Jenny Lind; and letter, December 29, 1860, "Lizzie" to "Willie," concerning the political future of the United States. #38-490
- Hubard-Randolph-Carter Family Papers ca. 1832-1941, ca. 3,000 items.
  Papers of the Hubard, Randolph and Carter families, primarily of Albemarle County, Virginia. Items of interest are an indenture, November 13, 1834, in regard to the property of Sarah Champe Carter, George Wythe Randolph to his sister-in-law, congratulating her on the birth of her son, with an interesting commentary on daughters; Sally Champe Randolph to her husband B. F. Randolph, December 14, 1853, describing her mother's illness and touching on contemporary medical techniques, Harriet Parkhill to Isaetta Hubard, concerning her education, hoop skirts and the tragedy at Harper's Ferry, January 11, 1860. #4717,-a, -b including 249, 2424, -a,-e, and 5885
- Hubard Family Papers ca. 1750-1950, ca. 12,000 items.
  Correspondence, legal, and business documents of Robert T. Hubard, Sr., and his descendants of "Rosny" and "Chellowe" in Buckingham County. Included is a December 22, 1854, letter from Charles Jones to Robert Hubard in which Jones writes for a slave "Walker" who wishes Hubard to buy his wife who is going to be sold. #8039
- Mary E. Huger Letter 1808, 1 item.
  Letter, May 25, 1808, from Huger to Eliza Nelson, concerning her health, her attendant "who has all the simplicity of a child of nature," her wish "to establish a little manufactory" and hopes to have a "spinning machine" at home the following year, the alcohol problem of her brother Francis and its effects. #3515
- Huger-Pinckney Family Papers 1753-ca. 1855, 29 items.
  Contains several letters of Elizabeth Pinckney and her son Thomas, a Revolutionary War general from South Carolina, mainly about personal affairs. Microfilm 1256; (#6019)
- Elizabeth Carter Hull Diary 1928, 1 item.
  Diary kept sporadically during 1928 by Hull of [Baltimore, Maryland], discussing her advertising classes (January), facts about department stores (May), and training and working at a department store (October), possibly in the Advertising Department of Stewart and Company, and her interest in bookplate collecting. Quotes of authors on varying subjects. #3521
- Fannie Page Hume 1860, 1 item
  Scrapbook of Fannie Page Hume (d. 1864) primarily containing poetry and verses. #838
- Fannie Page Hume 1858-1862, ca. 25 items.
  Diaries of this Orange County, Virginia resident. Detailed daily entries concerning the war, family local news, and nearby troops. #1713-h
- Hunter-Garnett Papers 1704-1912, 74 boxes.
  Primarily the papers of Robert Mercer Taliaferro Hunter of Essex County, Virginia, member of the U.S. House of Representatives and Senate before the Civil War and appointed Confederate Secretary of State. The collection contains a sizeable amount of correspondence generated by women including Mary Evelina Hunter (Mrs. R.M.T.), Virginia Brooke, Nancy Buchanan, Martha Dandridge, Sarah Pendleton Dandridge, Maria Garnett, Mary Garnett, Jane Hunter, Martha T. Hunter, Martha F. Hunter, and several others. Also of interest are the essays and writings of Martha F. Hunter, R. M. T.'s sister. #38-45
- Hunter-Moseley-Lovitt-James Papers 1766-1780, ca. 26 pieces
  Collection consists of tithtables and three marriage bonds dated December 5, 1766, October 7, 1775, and January 31, 1780. #38-635
- Grace Fenton Garnett Hunter 1838-1839, 1 item.
  Typed copy of journal of Grace Fenton Garnett Hunter, who was born August 4, 1817 and probably died in the winter of 1839, although no date is given. #1896
- John D. Imboden Papers 1830-1940, ca. 3,500 items
  John D. Imboden was a lawyer, a member of the Virginia House of Delegates, a Confederate veteran, and finally a developer of mineral lands and railroads. Personal correspondence includes letters to his first wife, Eliza Allen McCue (1824-1857) and with his fourth and fifth wives, Annie Harper Lockett Imboden and Florence Johnson Crockett Imboden, as well as his two of his daughters, Martha Russie and Helen McGuire. #38-23
- Irvine-Saunders Papers 1800-1865, ca. 3000 items.
  Personal, legal, and commercial papers of the Watts, Saunders, and Featherston families and their connections, of Prince Edward Botetourt, Campbell, and Bedford counties, Virginia. Correspondence includes Mrs. Mary Watts, widow of William Watts, with her children, grandchildren and friends [1800-1839], overlapping with the correspondence of her daughter, Mrs. Alice Saunders and her husband, Fleming Saunders [1778-1858] ca. 1830-1860. Also of interest are 10 letters from Captain J. C. Featherston, 9th Alabama Regt. to his wife March 28-June 19, 1865. #38-33
- Indenture 1865 August 19, 1 item.
  An indenture which binds a "Free girl of color," Susan, to John F. Hawkins to learn to be a house servant. #6060
- Elsie Fowkes Jackson 1951, 2 items.
  Typescript (mimeographed), Jackson's play, A Pair of Epaulets, was written to encourage young girls to become nurses. It is accompanied by a newsclipping re the play. #6589-f
- Phoebe Jackson Account Book 1843-1845, 1 item.
  Phoebe Jackson was a nurse who specialized in cupping and leeching in Petersburg, Virginia, from the 1830's-1850's. Born a slave she was emancipated by Jane Minor, herself a free Black and a well-known nurse. She enters into the book many visits to servants. #2120.
- Louis Isaac Jaffe Papers 1931-1949, 430 items.
  Articles, reports, speeches, newsclippings, pamphlets, and other printed material, photographs and some correspondence, all pertaining to subjects of concern to Jaffe as editor of the "Virginian-Pilot." Among the correspondents is Amelia Earhart. #9924-k
- Edward Wilson James Papers 1635-1906, ca. 2000 items.
  Records of the James Family of Lower Norfolk County, Virginia consisting mostly of legal and business records. There are occasional slave bills of sale such as an 1829 bill for the sale of a woman. Also of interest is the will of Elizabeth James (1789) and numerous marriage bonds (18th century). #38-402
- Thomas Jefferson Papers 1780, 1818, 2 items.
  Includes letter, August 8, 1780, from Martha Jefferson to Madam. #3668
- Catherine Coyle Underwood Johnson Collection 1854-1857, 8 items.
  Eight letters from this Centreville, Indiana woman, to her brother John Ingle Underwood in Washington, D. C. and Charleston, West Virginia. Highlights family life and personal topics. #1560
- Mary Johnston Papers 1898-1936, ca. 4,000 items.
  Author and suffragette. Correspondence, diaries (1907-19150, accounts, speeches, and other papers, concerning Miss Johnston's literary pursuits and her advocacy of women's suffrage. The correspondence with her publishers and agents concern book and article titles, contracts, royalties, public taste, criticism of her work, and motion picture and dramatic rights. Includes manuscripts and galley proofs of Audrey(1902), Lewis Rand(1908), The Far Country(unfinished and unpublished), and others. Other correspondence and speeches concern her activities with various organizations on behalf of women's rights. Correspondents include Viola Allen. Rebecca Harding Davis, Margaret Deland, Zona Gale, Ellen Glasgow, Fola LaFollette, Cary Gholson (Glasgow) McCormick, Marian McDowell, Margaret Meredith, Nannie Minor, Mrs. Walter Hines Page, Mrs. Roger Pryor, Eleanor Robson, Anna Katherine Gren Rohls, Anna Howard Shaw, May Sinclair, Alice Tyler, Ellen C. Whitney, and Elinor Wyllie. #3588, -a, -b
- Johnston-Wright Family Papers 1858-1900, 625 items.
  Papers of this North Garden and Hardware, Virginia family; personal correspondence of Mollie Johnston and Sallie Johnston Wright concerning family matters. #38-8
- Benjamin Washington Jones Papers 1902-1923, 35 items.
  Papers concern yearly reunions of the Surry Light Artillery of Confederate Veterans. Georgiette Holmes letters discuss reunions and Mrs. W. E. Harris' letter of March 1910 solicits help in beginning an organization for descendants of veterans to educate them on the war; that slavery was not the cause alone. #38-467
- Chiang May-ling Soong (Madame Chiang Kai-Shek) 1932, 1 item.
  Letter, April 15, 1932, Madame Chiang Kai-Shek, Nanking China, to Miss Helena Koiner. #3324
- Elizabeth (Runk) Kayan Diaries 1938-1957, 9 volumes.
  Diaries of Kayan recording the daily routine at "Hollymead," a farm near Proffit, Virginia. In addition to the farm routines she mentions the weather and social activities. There are frequent references to her brother, University of Virginia Biology Professor Benjamin Franklin Dewes Runk. #3556-b
- L. L. Kean Letters 1844-1847, 3 items.
  Form letter sent by Helen Keller requesting aid for the American Foundation for the Blind. #2277
- Kennon Family Papers 1817-1903, 950 items
  Personal and business papers of William Henry Kennon and his son William Upshur Kennon of "Norwood," Powhatan County, Virginia. Correspondence includes members of the Deas, Heth, Kennon, Randolph, Selden, and Murray families. Scattered letters from various women in these families. #38-95
- Kentucky Slave Contract 1814, 1 item.
  Bill of sale, October 3, 1814, between W. Crawford of Nicholas County, Kentucky, and James Pipen of the same county authorizing the sale of a female slave for $350 to William Crawford. #4679
- Frances Parkinson Keyes Papers 1950, 1 item.
  Keys writes on August 28, 1950, to Richmond R. Baker explaining that she has not responded to his letter earlier because of her involvement in "creative work," and a forthcoming move from her country house to Boston, Massachusetts. She asks Baker if she may mention his name in the forward as one of her collaborators. #6841-g
- Sigismunda Stribling Kimball Journal 1860-1863, 1 item.
  Detailed daily farm business entered by this woman from Mount Jackson in the Shenandoah Valley. There are frequent references to slaves (hands) and a detailed account concerning the return of runaway slaves with Union troops to rescue their wives and families. #2534
- William King-Annie Leftwich Papers 1844-1867, ca. 60 items.
  The correspondence of William King of Saltville, Virginia, chiefly war letters to his wife Anne (Nannie) Leftwich King, at Lynchburg and Richmond, Virginia, concerning his camp and battle experiences as a Confederate artilleryman at Manassas Junction, Centerville, and Fairfax Court house, Virginia. #2798
- Klipstein Family Papers 1823-1868, 55 items.
  Chiefly correspondence of Dr. Philip Klipstein of Fauquier County. Included are receipts for hire of black women. #2234
- Marquise de Lafayette, Marie Adrienne de Noailles Letter 1794 October 17, 1 item.
  The Marquise de Lafayette, wife of the Marquis de Lafayette appeals to the Committee of General Safety, Department of the Haute-Loire, District of Brioude for justice, maintaining that there was no motive for her arrest and that her certificate of good citizenship proves her innocence. She requests deportation to the United States and mentions in a marginal note the execution of her grandmother, mother and sister the previous July. #8739-b
- William H. Laird Papers 1940-1947, 1394 items.
  Papers of William H. Laird of Charlottesville, Virginia, consisting of correspondence among Laird and family members when he was serving as chaplain for the 8th Evacuation Hospital in Europe. Also included are photographs, diaries, and maps. Bulk of the correspondence is between Laird and his wife, Constance and their children. Topics discussed include Arab women (May 23, 1843), the argument over the necessity of nurses in the unit (June 8, 1943), and the promotion of nurses (August 15, 1943). Letters from home provide insight into the effects of the second World War upon family members left behind. #999-a
- James Lanier and Martha Tabb Green Lanier Papers ca. 1800-1860, ca. 35 items.
  Manuscript verses and other papers regarding James Lanier (1792-1856) of Danville, Va. and his wife Martha Tabb Green Lanier. #546, 546-a
- Latané Family Papers 1650-1898, ca. 710 items.
  A collection of items pertaining to the Latané family of Essex County, Virginia. Included are correspondence, business and legal papers, papers in regards to military and religious matters, school notebooks, and certificates of graduation for schools of the University of Virginia. The early eighteenth century correspondence contains many letters from Henry Latané and his wife, Anne, London, England, to his brother, Lewis and his third wife, Mary (Deane), South Farnham Parish, Essex County. After her husband's death in 1732, Mary (Deane) Latane managed the property that came to her and her children, with the help of her cousin, William Beverley. There are several letters, 1733-1750, from Beverley discussing the settlement of her husband's estate and the sale of her tobacco. #6490
- Sarah Goodwich Leach 1860-1872, 1 item.
  Diary and recipe book of Sarah Goodwich Leach. #Microfilm M-1389; 2603
- League of Woman Voters Papers ca. 1940-1985, ca. 1500 items.
  Records of the Charlottesville and Albemarle County, Virginia organization including printed material from the national and state leagues, as well as the chapter's "Monthly Bulletin," minutes of Boards of Directors meetings and of annual meetings, membership lists, by-laws, committee study reports, and other data. #8974, etc.
- Lee Family Papers 1714-1930, ca. 15,000 items.
  This collection consists primarily of the papers of Arthur Lee (1740-1792) and those of his brothers, Richard Henry (1732-1794) and William (1735-1795) from "Stratford Hall," Westmoreland County, Virginia. Besides the Lees' papers and those of their relatives, there are included papers of Mrs. Catherine MacCauley, among others. The major portion of these papers has been microfilmed under the title, "Lee Family Papers, 1742-1795;" a published guide to the microfilm edition is available. #Microfilm M-1714-1721; 38-112, etc.
- Robert E. Lee Letter 1864, 1 item.
  Letter, March 24, 1864, from Lee to Mrs. J. S. Hesikell concerning the return of table cloths that she sent to Lee's forces. #38-186
- Marco Leeflang 1986, 1 item.
  About Casanova: Vol. 2: Correspondence between Macro Leeflang and Charles Samaran [and others]. Electrostatic copy, original letters in possession of Leeflang. Correspondence re Casanova between Leeflang and Samaran, a French historian and Casanova scholar, and Jeanne Samaran, his daughter, together with correspondence with Jacques Marsan, the Touring club of France, Prince Alfons Clary-Aldringen, and Ambassador Gian Franco Pompeii all on some aspect of Casanova scholarship. #9256-r.
- Leftwich Family Papers 1843-1863, ca. 10 items.
  Miscellaneous letters of the Leftwich family of Lynchburg and vicinity, Virginia. Sarah Leftwich wrote to her brother Thomas Leftwich of Mississippi of trying to sell Violet, who is an ill-tempered slave. "We have no reason in the world for selling her, except that she will not live in peace with the servants and prefers to be sold. To say the truth she is the vilest tempered being I ever saw..." #3129
- Joel Leftwich Papers 1780-1890, 500 items.
  Correspondence, financial and legal papers of General Joel Leftwich. Personal correspondence includes mention of his granddaughters. Of special itnerest are letters between Joel Leftwich and his friends concerning college life at Randolph-Macon College during the 1840's and their perceptions of the women they were courting. #38-32, 38-147
- Lewis and Latané Family Papers 1757-1975, 750 items.
  Primarily the paper of Warner Lewis and his family of Tappahannock and Essex counties in Virginia. His brother, Joseph L. Lewis, seemed in constant financial trouble, but did write of a particular woman on August 11, 1817: "Yesterday I saw a young woman whose acute nose and chin and black eyes made my heart beater quarter seconds for an hour..." While he never married his brother Warner married three times with 14 children. Joseph, through letters, expounding on marriage to his brother. Few items of correspondence relating to women. #1525, -a
- James M. Lewis Papers 1744-1860, ca. 45 items.
  Correspondence and papers of the Lewis, Latané, and Taliaferro families. Items of interest include a gossipy letter, September 1, 1860, from Elizabeth Noel who was staying at White Sulphur Springs, to her daughter(?) telling stories about what went on at the resort, and about a lady who dared not to wear hoops. Furthermore, there are the letters Warner Lewis wrote to his wife, Ann Lewis, during the War of 1812 which reflect intimacy and marriage. #38-418
- Judson A. Lewis Papers 1883-1895, 8 items.
  Letterbrooks and scrapbooks of Judson A. Lewis, U. S. consul to Sierra Leone in West Africa, and a diary kept by his wife which mentions Stanley [William Stanley?] #7665
- Margaret Lewis Daybook 18th century, 1 volume.
  Typescript sketch, 23 pages, entitled the Valley Manuscript. Purported to be an 18th century commonplace book of an ancestor of Meriwether Lewis. This so-called day-book is wholly fictitious. Someone has woven together many events of Lewis family history in this form. It was first published in 1869 in The land we love. It was edited by H. E. Van Gelder and published in the Salem Times-Register in March 1940. On 1939 August 24 Miss Annie Belle Martin of "Kinderton," Hampden-Sydney, Va., wrote to acting archivist W. Edwin Hemphill, it was produced for a contest by a "college girl." #591
- Mallory Family Papers 1728-1835, ca. 200 items.
  Business papers of Nathan and John Mallory, small planters, of Orange County, Virginia. Included is a February 2, 1758 bill of sale for a black woman. #38-140
- Moses H. Mann Deposition 1824 February 25 & October 9, 1 item.
  Deposition of Moses H. Mann taken in Richmond, 1824, for the Superior Court of Chancery in Lewisburg regard to business ethics and the sale of a slave woman. #8979-z
- Correspondence written to members of the Birckhead family 1839-1891, ca. 15 items.